A Guide to the Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Art Reference Files FA522
Rockefeller Archive Center
Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Art Reference Files
1934-2008
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman (1910-2004)
Rockefeller, Mary French (1910-1997)
Uht, Carol Kinzel
Lutkins, Kendall P.
Talamo, Leith Rutherfurd
FA522
10.25 Cubic Feet 22 card-file boxes, 13 letter-size document boxes, 1 legal-size document box
Arrangement
The Art Reference Files are arranged into two series: Series 1 - Art Reference Card Files, and Series 2 - Art Files.
Scope and Contents
Laurance S. Rockefeller's Art Reference Files contain documentation of his and his wife Mary French Rockefeller's personal collection of fine art, sculpture, porcelain, silver, decorative arts, furniture, and jewelry, and include materials on Native American, African, and Asian art.
The collection consists primarily of a card-file catalogue of the collection, which was created and maintained by the Rockefeller Family office, and of various art files maintained by his curators, Carol Kinzel Uht, Kendall P. Lutkins, and Leith Talamo.
Biographical / Historical
Carol Kinzel Uht, Nelson A. Rockefeller's curator from 1949 to 1978, helped with the early cataloguing and documentation of LSR's art collection.
Biographical / Historical
Kendall P. Lutkins began working under Nelson A. Rockefeller and became NAR's joint curator with Cynthia Altman after Carol Uht's death in 1978. Lutkins' area of expertise was in the decorative arts, silver, porcelain, and pottery. In the spring of 1979, Lutkins coordinated the full reappraisal of LSR's art collection and his other tangible property. Over the years she assisted LSR with the management of his porcelain, silver, and other collections, advising him on his porcelain purchases or sales, and assisting with the identification or description of other items.
Biographical / Historical
Leith Rutherfurd Talamo began working for LSR in 1998. A trained conservator, and the daughter of family friends, she also headed up Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center's Art Committee. Her work for LSR included reviewing, identifying, and organizing his collection of paintings and artwork; arranging for framing or restoration work; recommending pieces for de-accessioning and arranging for their donation; managing appraisals; and photographing the collections.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted.
Materials in the Laurance S. Rockefeller papers relating to communications with his immediate family, his personal finances, and other intra-family matters, are restricted until 2029, twenty years from the date of gift.
Rockefeller family -- Art collections
- Art Reference Card Files, 1940s - 2005; 1; 4.82 Cubic Feet 22 card file boxes
  Scope and Contents
  LSR's Art Reference Card Files were first created in the 1940s, to be a central file and record of the fine art belonging to Laurance S. and Mary French Rockefeller. The files were kept and maintained at the Rockefellers' New York apartment, at 834 Fifth Avenue, though the family office in Rockefeller Center may have started the file.
  Cards were created for each art object, recording how, when, and from whom it was acquired (by purchase, bequest, or gift), and often including a full description, insurance valuation, price, subsequent appraisal values, location, and in some cases photos. Cards were updated as information changed, and Polaroid photos were later taken of many of the items as documentation of the collection. Many of the cards also carried a catalogue number, which connected the card description to inventories of LSR's and MFR's collection.
  The cards were grouped according to the item location, and then filed by category. Inventoried locations include: the apartment at 834 Fifth Avenue (New York), Kent House and the Kent House Shrine (Tarrytown, NY), Echo Acre (Woodstock, VT), and LSR's New York Office (Room 5600). There are also card sections for other locations, including the Marsh-Billings-Rockefeller Mansion in Woodstock, VT, the Valley Ranch House and JY Ranch in Jackson Hole, Wyoming, and LSR's Fishers Island (NY) residence.
  Categories of art items include: Fine Art, Sculpture, Porcelain and Pottery, Furniture and Decoration, Rugs, Textiles, Silver, and Jewelry. When appropriate, categories such as Fine Art, Sculpture, and Porcelain, were further broken down into Western Fine Art, Chinese Porcelain, Indian Sculpture, etc. Other categories included African Art, Native American Artwork, and Antiquities.
  These rules of arrangement seemingly worked well until LSR began to disperse his artwork, through sale, gifts, and ultimately through his estate distributions. An "Out" category designated deaccessioned items, though the label also applied more generally to any object that left the apartment or other site.
  The "Out" files comprise nearly a quarter of the Art Card Files. The "Out" cards form a second, parallel file to the main card files, but in general it is hard to know how reliable the distinction is. Some cards clearly indicate the disposition of an item, and in other cases its disposition may be inferred. Several cards are simply marked with an "X" to indicate that items are no longer owned. Lacking information on the disposition, it is difficult to know whether items were removed, or the cards misfiled. In other cases, information on a piece may still be found in the main files. Finally, the "Out" files do not include family selections of artwork from LSR's estate. The cards for these objects are found at the end of the Card Files series.
  A series of photographs of the paintings, furniture, and decorative objects at 834 Fifth Avenue is the final component of the Art Card Files. These 4" x 6" color snapshots appear to have been taken in the mid- to late-1990s. They may be photos Leith R. Talamo took to document the collection. Photos are nominally arranged by room, but the arrangement within and among these files is not reliable.
  - Kent House and Guest House (Box 1)
    Polaroid photos of Kent House rooms; numbered Polaroid photos of furniture items with appraisal value in various Kent House Guest House rooms (KHG 1- 29).
  - Kent House Shrine (Box 1)
    Polaroid photos of furniture, paintings, sculpture, and exterior views. File includes art index cards for a few pieces (giving description and provenance information). Photos numbered 1-33, with some gaps and duplicates. Set of photocopied images (7 pages) folded at back of file.
    The Shrine, or Japanese Shrine, was built on the Kykuit grounds between 1908-1910.
  - Kent House - Porcelain and Pottery (Western, Chinese, Modern) (Box 1)
    Figurines, dinner services and other sets, tableware,vases, decorative pieces, and lamps. Polaroid photos and art index cards with description and provenance information. Photos include pencilled notations concerning location (room) and valuation. Photos are numbered KH 207 - KH 290, with some gaps and some photos out of sequence; includes some unnumbered photos (especially for several lamps).
    The file is divided into the following sections: Western Porcelain and Pottery, Chinese Porcelain and Pottery, Modern Pieces, and a small section of Chinese porcelain and pottery arranged by Chait Appraisal number (Chait 1-11, 13).
  - Kent House - Indian and Southeast Asian Pieces (Box 1)
    Polaroid photos of two Kirman carpets and a Tibetan tanka (KH 21, 73, 323). Photocopied image of Burmese gilt lacquered wood figure of the Buddha and catalogue card (SC-61).
  - Kent House - Japanese and Korean Furniture and Decoration (Box 1)
    Dishes, figurines, vases, lacquered box, lamps (KH 84, 231-232, 267, 269-271, 506, 195, unnumbered). Polaroid photos and a few catalogue cards.
  - Kent House - Japanese Fine Art (Box 1)
    Polaroid photos, catalogue cards, and some negatives.
  - Kent House and Guest House - Fine Art (A-Z) (Box 2)
    Polaroid photos, catalogue cards, and negatives. Paintings, filed alphabetically by artist, in separate series for Kent House and the Guest House.
  - Kent House - Sculpture (Box 2)
    Photos, catalogue cards, and negatives, arranged alphabetically by artist.
  - Kent House - Western Furniture and Decoration (Box 3)
    Polaroid photos, catalogue cards, and negatives, arranged by room, Kent House and Guest House or cottage. Photo numbers KH 1-206 and KH 504-513, with gaps. File also includes unnumbered photos and catalog cards, and numbered, but unidentified Uht furniture negatives 495, 501, 514-528, 768.
  - Kent House - Glass (Box 3)
  - Echo Acre (Box 4)
    Furnishings and Fine Art: general photos of rooms and fixtures; Western Fine Art and Sculpture, arranged alphabetically by artist; Furniture and Decoration, Porcelain and Pottery (photo file only - Polaroid photos with pencilled location and valuation); Chinese Fine Art, Furniture, Porcelain and Pottery (primarily photos); Japanese Fine Art (includes catalogue cards and negatives); Southeast Asian art; Rugs and Carpets; Office (Fine Art alphabetical file and Furniture).
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Fine Art and Sculpture (Box 5)
    Alphabetical files by artist of Paintings and Sculpture. Box also includes small section labeled "Copies" (paintings that LSR had had copied, prior to his donating the originals).
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Glass (Box 5)
    Art Index catalogue cards for Glass, arranged by type and number. Card index only, no photos.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Western Porcelain and Pottery (Box 6)
    File includes Polaroid photos, catalogue cards, and negatives. Dinner services and other sets, plates, bowls, figurines.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Meissen Figures (Box 6)
    LSR's collection of eighteenth-century Meissen porcelain bird figurines.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Chait Appraisals (Chinese Porcelain) (Box 6)
    Photos, catalogue cards, and some negatives, arranged by Chait appraisal number (Chait 3-86, with gaps). Chinese porcelain vases, figures, jugs, and dishes.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Chinese Fine Art, Chinese Furniture and Decoration, Chinese Porcelain and Pottery (Box 6)
    A section on Chinese sculpture is empty.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Japanese Fine Art and Japanese Porcelain and Pottery (Box 6)
    A section on Japanese Sculpture was empty.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Japanese Furniture and Decoration (Box 7)
    Includes set of catalogue cards for collection of Japanese inro and netsuke, with insurance appraisal by Sotheby's Parke Bernet, 1980. Provenance not indicated.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Indian and Southeast Asian Fine Art and Decoration (Box 7)
    Polaroid photos, negatives, and catalogue cards for paintings and a few brass objects. Several of the paintings were purchased in India in 1962-1963.
    A section on Indian sculpture is empty.
  - Antiquities (Sculpture) (Box 7)
    Items located in LSR's New York office or at Kent House. Sino-Tibetan and Tibetan buddhas and other figures (SC 55-196, with gaps); four reproductions of African statues. Catalogue cards and negatives.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Furniture and Decoration (Metal and Brass) (Box 7)
    Catalogue card file. Western and Asian (Japan, Korea, China, Persia) pieces in brass, copper, bronze. File also includes cards for 2 pieces of wooden furniture and a lamp made from a Japanese vase. (Furniture index nos. R 3-69 and V 3-4, with gaps.)
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Western Furniture and Decoration (Box 7)
    Numbered series of Polaroid photos, plus some negatives and catalogue cards, roughly sorted by floor and room. Furniture pieces and decorative objects.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Furniture and Decoration (Objects and Little Things) (Box 8)
    Photo File. Polaroid photos showing objects, framed photos, books, and knick-knacks in situ on table tops and furniture, floors 14 -16. Several photos dated May 2, 2000.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Rugs and Carpets (Box 8)
    Polaroid photos.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Textiles (Box 8)
    Polaroid photos of fabric, clothing, and dolls.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Books (Box 8)
    Includes catalogue cards for a few selected books, plus snapshots of book shelves and collections.
  - New York Office (Room 5600) - Western Fine Art and Sculpture (Box 8)
  - New York Office (Room 5600) - Antiquities (Box 8)
    Buddhas, figurines, pots, and vases. File consists mainly of Polaroid photos.
  - New York Office (Room 5600) - Native American Art (Box 8)
    Pottery bowls, Navajo blankets. File includes wooden Hawaiian bowl.
  - New York Office (Room 5600) - General (Box 8)
    Art and decorative pieces of no specific value (NSV).
  - Out - Furniture and Decoration (Thrift Shop and other Donations?) (Box 9)
    Photos filed under divider ambiguously labeled "Loans." Small furniture and decorative objects, many of which were donated to MSKCC Thrift Shop. Includes some catalogue cards and negatives. Not all photos indicate the disposition of the item; some items may be misfiled here.
  - Out - General (Box 9)
    Furniture, glass, and decorative items. Photos, with some catalogue cards and negatives, generally marked with an "X." Thrift shop donations and other gifts. The disposition of the items is not always noted.
  - Asian and Indian Furniture and Decoration, Textiles, Antiquities - Out (Box 9)
    Photos, with some catalogue cards and negatives, generally marked with an "X." Thrift shop donations and other gifts. The disposition of the items is not always noted.
  - Rugs and Carpets - Out (Box 9)
    Photo file. Navajo rugs (JY Ranch), Tibetan rug. Gifts.
  - Porcelain and Pottery - Out (Box 9)
    Western, Chinese, and Japanese; dinner plates and other services, serving pieces, figurines, vases. Catalogue cards and some photos, generally marked with an "X." Donations, returns, gifts. Items from Woodstock and 834 Fifth Ave. The disposition of the items is not always noted.
  - Woodstock Mansion (Furniture and Decoration) (Box 9)
    Catalogue cards for furnishings at Woodstock Mansion. Most cards flagged with a red metal clip. File may be considered an "Out" file, as the furniture was donated to the National Park Service along with the Mansion.
    File includes cards for an item at the Woodstock Inn and one from the Fisher's Island house.
  - Photographs of Fine Art (Paintings and Prints) (Box 9)
    Unlabeled set of 4x6 color prints (with duplicates) of approximately 40 framed paintings and prints from LSR's collection. It is possible that the photos document deaccessioned artwork, but the particular significance of this set of photos is not known.
  - Native American Jewelry - Out (Box 9)
    Catalogue card file. CRFT 30-69. Mainly Navajo, jewelry and belts.
  - African Fine Art - Out (Box 9)
    Catalogue cards, photos, and negatives. African paintings, watercolors, and sculpture.
  - African Fine Art (Paintings, Watercolors, Sculpture) (Box 10)
    Polaroid photos, catalogue cards, and negatives. File includes a couple of Haitian artists. A few cards carry notations on the gifting or other disposition of the artwork, but it is not clear whether or not the file should be considered an "Out" file.
  - African Fine Art - Artists' Index (Box 10)
    Catalogue cards and negatives for African artists and some American folk artists, with an inventory list of the paintings and watercolors in LSR's collection. In most cases the cards indicate (with an "X") items that have been deaccessioned. Several entries are marked with an "X" followed by a "B," but it is not known what the B represents.
  - African Furniture and Decoration (Box 10)
    Polaroid photos and catalogue cards or simple file cards.
  - African Sculpture (Box 10)
    Photos, catalogue cards, and negatives. Includes an Artists' Index inventory listing of African sculpture.
  - Native American Art - Out (Box 10)
    Catalogue cards. Includes rugs labeled "Woodstock" and "Turner" (CRFT 1-11, 17-18), jewelry (CRFT 70-77), baskets, and pottery.
  - Native American Art - JY Ranch (Box 10)
    Catalogue cards. Paintings by Paxton, Wilcox,and others. Baskets, jewelry, beading, pottery, rugs and weavings(CRFT 76-507, with gaps). Includes items at Valley Ranch.
  - Native American Rugs - JY Ranch (Box 10)
    Photos, with captions, of six [Navajo?] rugs purchased in 1968.
  - Negatives - Porcelain and Pottery (Box 10)
    Negatives file: Charles Uht negatives, numbers 547, 585-604, 701, 750-752, 856, 864-867, 871, 884-899, 916-940. Some of the envelopes include very general descriptions of the items. It is not known whether there is any particular significance to this set of negatives (e.g., whether they represent deaccessioned items, or whether they are simply loose negatives). We have made no attempt to match the negatives with catalogue cards in the collection.
  - Art Collection Labels (Box 10)
    "Collection Laurance S. Rockefeller" labels (or inventory slips?), for assorted paintings, watercolors, pastels, and prints in LSR's collection. Some labels include location information in pencil on the back.
  - Fine Art and Sculpture - Out (A - L) (Box 11)
    Alphabetical file by artist, A - L. Catalogue cards, photos, and negatives.
  - Fine Art and Sculpture - Out (M - U) (Box 12)
    Alphabetical by artist, M - U. Catalogue cards, photos, and negatives. Early American, folk art, and other anonymous pieces are filed under U, "Unknown." The Unknown category also includes photos of several horse prints, and miscellaneous negatives.
  - Fine Art and Sculpture - Out (V - Z) (Box 13)
    Alphbetical by artist, V-Z. Catalogue cards, negatives, and some photos.
  - Asian Fine Art - Out (Box 13)
    Japanese, Korean, and Chinese prints and watercolors.
  - Western Sculpture - Out (Box 13)
  - Indian and Southeast Asian Fine Art and Sculpture - Out (Box 13)
    Catalogue cards, photos, and negatives.
  - Jewelry (Box 13)
    Jewelry cards,sorted into categories: Bracelets; Clips and Pins; Cufflinks, Vest Buttons, and Studs; Earrings; Miscellaneous; Necklaces and Pendants; Rings; Watches; Watches (LSR). Includes Jewelry Index and catalogue codes at front of file. Cards include description and provenance information.
  - Jewelry - Photos (Box 13)
    Black and white Polaroid photos of selected jewelry pieces belonging to MFR and to LSR. Photos include penciled references to the Jewelry catalogue index numbers. Photos are numbered in two series: 1-12 M and 1-7 L. There are also unidentified references to "Card" numbers written in pencil on the back of the photos.
  - Silver - Index by Category (Box 14)
    Silver card file and index, arranged by category (coded A-Z): Flatware; Tea and Coffee Services; Children's pieces; Trays, Plates, and Platters; Dishes and Bowls; Tumblers, Porringers, and Mugs; Miscellaneous Dining Room silver; Miscellaneous Non-Dining Room silver. Includes items at 834 Fifth Avenue, Woodstock, and Kent House. Cards include description and provenance information. Index includes information on marks and identification. File also includes photos of silver display cabinets (location not indentified).
  - Silver - Kent House (Box 14)
    File contains catalogue cards and negatives for silver items at Kent House. Flatware and Silver. Silver arranged by Robinson 1980 appraisal numbers, T1 - T59. Catalogue cards and negatives. Cards flagged with blue metal clips (for Tarrytown, Kent House).
  - Silver - Kent House - Photos (Box 14)
    File of Polaroid photos, numbered T1 - T82. The "T" numbers on the photos correspond to the 1980 Robinson appraisal numbers on the catalogue card files for Kent House silver (there are cards for items T1 -T59 only).
  - Silver Flatware - Kent House (Box 15)
    Catalogue cards and negatives.
  - Silver Flatware and Cutlery - Kent House - Photos (Box 15)
    Polaroid photos, numbered TF (Tarrytown - Flatware) 1-23 (with a few gaps). The numbers refer to the Robinson appraisal, November 22, 2004, of the silver inventory in LSR's estate.
  - Silver Flatware - 834 Fifth Avenue (Box 15)
  - Silver Flatware and Cutlery - 834 Fifth Avenue - Photos (Box 15)
    Polaroid photos numbered F 1-118 (with some gaps). The umbers refer to the Robinson appraisal, November 22, 2004, of the silver inventory in LSR's estate.
  - Silver - 834 Fifth Avenue (Items 1 - 45) (Box 15)
    Catalogue cards, negatives, and photos of silver at 834 Fifth Avenue, arranged by Robinson 1980 appraisal numbers (items 1-45).
    The catalogue card file for Silver at 834 Fifth Avenue was originally filed as two sets of cards, each arranged in numerical order according to the Robinson appraisal numbers. As the two card files complemented each other, and as there was no apparent distinction between the two series, they have been integrated here into one numerical series (in boxes 15-17, items 1-299).
  - Silver - 834 Fifth Avenue (Items 46 - 190) (Box 16)
    Catalogue cards, negatives, and photos of silver at 834 Fifth Avenue, arranged by Robinson 1980 appraisal numbers (items 46-190).
  - Silver - 834 Fifth Avenue (Items 191 - 299) (Box 17)
    Catalogue cards, negatives, and photos of silver at 834 Fifth Avenue, arranged by Robinson 1980 appraisal numbers (items 181-299).
  - Silver - [834 Fifth Avenue] - Photos (Items 300 - 342) (Box 17)
    Polaroid photos of silver items numbered 300-342. The files do not include any catalogue cards or other description for these items, which appear to be from 834 Fifth Avenue. Since the item numbers in this set of photos follow exactly on the silver inventory in boxes 15-17 (items 1-299), presumably they also designate items listed in the Robinson 1980 appraisal.
  - Silver - Unidentified Photos (Box 17)
    Unidentified set of Polaroid photos of silver items. Photos numbered 303-317. (Not the same items - nor the same background - as the other "300" series of photos.)
  - Silver sent for repair or marked for discard (Box 17)
    Photos of silver items from Kent House that were sent to Mr. Harwood for repair, August 8, 2000. Also includes photos of a few items marked for discard (or as not worth listing). Six Polaroid photos.
  - Silver - Negatives, 4" x 5" negatives (Box 17)
    Various Silver collection negatives, Uht nos. 203 - 860 (52 envelopes, with substantial gaps within the numerical range). About half the envelopes also include the item's identification number in LSR's Silver Index.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Photos by Room (Box 18)
    Photo file of paintings, furniture, and decorative objects, grouped roughly by room. The arrangement within and among file divisions is not reliable (many of the file dividers were missing labels), and images may be filed under more than one category or room. The photos appear to have been taken mostly around 1999, for documentation and as an inventory of furniture and artwork. (Some photos are date stamped 1994 or 1995, and there are also a few prints dated 2001.) Paintings and artwork have generally been photographed singly as individual items and not in context. In most cases duplicate prints have been removed. Box 18 is divided into the following headings: General photo files (individual art items), Gallery, Guest Room, Lucy's Room, Mrs. Rockefeller's Room, Ruth's Office and Hall, 14th Floor Hall, Mr. Rockefeller's Room, Master Bedroom, Mr. Rockefeller's Office, 15th Floor Landing and Hall, 15th Floor Dining Room, 15th Floor Powder Room, Stairs (15th-16th Floors).
    General
    A unidentified numbering scheme was applied to some photos, which are marked on the back with an "S" and a 3-digit number. These photos appear throughout the file, and in a possibly duplicate, but incomplete, general series.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Photos by Room (Box 19)